<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the King at White-Hall, January xxiij. 1675/6 by William Cave ...</title>
            <author>Cave, William, 1637-1713.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1676</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A31427</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1605</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5517</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12901167</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12901167</idno>
            <idno type="VID">95249</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A31427)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95249)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 977:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the King at White-Hall, January xxiij. 1675/6 by William Cave ...</title>
                  <author>Cave, William, 1637-1713.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 27 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Godbid for Richard Chiswell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1676.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:95249:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:95249:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached before the KING AT VVHITE-HALL, January <hi>xxiij.</hi> 1675/6. By <hi>WILLIAM CAVE,</hi> D. D. Chaplain in Ordinary to HIS MAJESTY.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="license">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Printed by His Majeſties ſpecial Command.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>W. Godbid</hi> for <hi>Richard Chiſwell,</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Roſe and Crown</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Church-yard,</hi> 1676.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:95249:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:95249:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached before the KING.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 COR. 2.11.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Leſt Satan ſhould get an advantage of us: for we are not ignorant of his devices.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THere can be no greater evidence of the weakneſs and degeneracy of the human Underſtanding, than that the Minds of Men are ſo eaſily impos'd upon, in Matters of the greateſt moment, and that with ſhews and phantaſtick Images of things, and ſuffer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be led aſide by little Arts of Sophiſtry
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:95249:3"/>and Inſinuation into paths immediately deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive both of their Nature and their Happineſs. Wiſdom and Folly are not ſo much to be meaſured by their reſpect to the petty affairs of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſtate, as by the ſtandard of Eternity, and the regard they bear to what unqueſtionably are our higheſt Intereſts, the concernments of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther World. We are wont with a very quick ſagacity to eſpy and decline a preſent evil, and with great ſollicitude to countermine the ſubtilties of an Adverſary that makes an attempt upon our Lives or Fortunes; and yet in the mean time can be ſupine and careleſs in the midſt of Enemies, whoſe deſigns reach beyond the preſent Life, and ſecurely walk over ſnares that are laid to ruin us forever.</p>
            <p>Being therefore placed in ſuch dangerous and unhappy circumſtances, nothing can be more prudent and reaſonable, than that we ſhould dwell at home, and keep our active and diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Faculties wakeful and vigilant, <hi>leſt Satan ſhould get an advantage of us: for we are not ignorant of his devices.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That there is a Fraternity and Combination of wicked and apoſtate Powers, ſpread up and down the World, which envy the happineſs of Mankind, and ſeek by all imaginable ways to undo them, is not only a Truth which the Holy
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:95249:3"/>Scriptures do frequently and expreſly declare and publiſh, but whereof the wiſer and more inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive part of the <hi>Gentile</hi> World were ſufficiently ſenſible,
<note place="margin">In vit. <hi>Dion.</hi> p. 958. non longe ab inir.</note> it being <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (as <hi>Plutarch</hi> tells us) <hi>one of their moſt ancient Traditions, that there were wicked and malignant Daemons, that envied good men, oppoſed their actions, and ſtrove to hinder them in the purſuit of Virtue, leſt continuing firm and ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt in a good courſe, they ſhould after death be more happy than themſelves:</hi> And elſewhere he tells us, 'twas the aſſertion of <hi>Xenocrates,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De <hi>Iſid.</hi> &amp; <hi>Oſyr.</hi> p. 361. tom. 2.</note> that <hi>the whole Aery Region is filled with mighty and potent Beings, ſurly and ill-natured, which rejoyce in doing miſchief, and never reſt 'till they have compaſſed their deſigns.</hi> A character that agrees exactly with the account which the Divine Oracles give us of theſe envious and malicious Spirits, that they <hi>walk to and fro throughout the earth,</hi> and go up and down from place to place, <hi>ſeeking reſt, but finding none,</hi> the chief of whom is <hi>the Prince of the Power of the Air, the Spirit that worketh in the children of diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Nature that's oppoſite to all Virtue and Goodneſs, <hi>the adverſary the Devil, who as a roaring Lion walks about, ſeeking whom he may devour;</hi> and what he cannot carry by force, he effects by ſubtilty, planting ſnares in every place, whereby the Sinner is <hi>taken captive by him at his will.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:95249:4"/>
            <p>Now that <hi>Satan</hi> may not get an advantage of us, either through ignorance of his devices, or want of conſideration to attend them, it may not poſſibly be unuſeful to enquire into, and examin ſome of the more ſucceſsful methods and trains of temptation, whereby the great Enemy of Souls is wont to blow up Mens reſolutions for Religion and a holy Life, for I take it for granted, that moſt Men at one time or another entertain ſerious thoughts about theſe matters, whoſe reſolutions perhaps might ripen into a kindly and generous piety, were they not ſtifled by the early ſnares and policies of the Tempter, whoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices are various and infinite; amongſt which, theſe four or five I conceive may principally chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge our conſideration; a ſecret disbelief of the truth of things, unjuſt repreſentations of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, a placing all Religion in a few empty and external pretenſions to piety and holineſs, a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance with ſuch Vices as have a ſhadow and reſemblance of Virtue, and the powerful influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of prevalent Examples. By which, amongſt many others, Mens religious purpoſes are ſtruck dead, at leaſt the edge and force of their Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours is taken off, and all our perſwaſives to Piety and Virtue are rendered improſperous and unſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful.</p>
            <p n="1">I. And firſt, Men are too often carried off
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:95249:4"/>from the paths of Virtue and Religion, by a ſecret disbelief of the truth of things, by giving way to doubts and ſcruples about ſome lighter and leſs important matters, whereby they are by degrees prepared to queſtion the greater and more fundamental Principles, the Notion of a Deity, and the expectations of another Life. When <hi>Satan</hi> attempted our firſt Parents, he began the aſſault with a <hi>peradventure,</hi> poſſibly God had not ſaid ſo, or would not be ſo ſevere as He had threatened; by which means he unſettled their Belief of the Divine Truth and Veracity, and having blown up this Fort, quickly made a breach for the whole Temptation to enter in. The firſt approaches of impiety are modeſt and baſhful, Men do not uſually commence Atheiſts at one leap, but ſuffer themſelves firſt to be entangled in ſome nice ſceptical diſſatisfactions, which in time grow up into a more ſtubborn and poſitive infidelity. And then how ordinary is it to hear ſuch Men, more than whiſper their Sentiments to this effect; that all Religion is but a trick of Art, a notion ſtarted by the fears of Men, hatch'd at firſt by ſome jealous Mind, or contrived by ſome crafty Sateſmen, to keep the World in peace and order; that the exiſtence of a ſupreme Being is but a dreadful and melancholy fancy, and the inviſible terrours of another World but painted
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:95249:5"/>flames, kindled in the warm brain of ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout and pious Preacher; that a future ſtate is but a precarious notion, and that there is no reaſon to believe what is at ſo vaſt a diſtance from us; that Good and Evil are but titular and imaginary things,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>D Laert.</hi> l. 9. in vit. <hi>Pyrrh.</hi> p. 670.</note> founded only <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (as <hi>Pyrrho</hi> the <hi>Sceptic</hi> affirmed of old) in cuſtom and human conſtitutions. The Author of the <hi>Book of Wiſdom</hi> fitly expreſſes the inward ſenſe of theſe Men, when he brings them in thus venting of their minds:
<note place="margin">Wiſd. 2.1, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Our life is ſhort and tedious, and in the death of a man there is no remedy, neither was there any man known to have returned from the grave; for we are born at all adventure, and we ſhall be hereafter as if we had never been: for the breath in our noſtrils is as ſmoke, and a little ſpark in the moving of our heart, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing extinguiſhed, our body ſhall be turned into aſhes, and ſpirit ſhall vaniſh as the ſoft air; and our name ſhall be forgotten in time, and no man ſhall have our works in remembrance; for our time is a very ſhadow that paſſeth away, and after our end there is no returning, for it is faſt ſealed, ſo that no man comes again.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This certainly is that <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which the <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>Syrach</hi> ſpeaks of, that bold daring temper, that makes light of whatever is ſacred, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolently affronts Omnipotence it ſelf. And when once Men have come thus far, to trample Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion under foot, they clap their wings, <hi>&amp; nos
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:95249:5"/>exequaet victoria coelo,</hi> as their Champion <hi>Lucretius</hi> begins the Triumph; and then 'tis kindneſs and modeſty, if they go no farther, and make not that, for which all Mankind beſides themſelves have ſo juſt a reverence and veneration, the object of their ſcorn and laughter, and the ſport of a wanton and a ſcurrilous wit. From ſuch Principles as theſe what can be expected, but the height of looſeneſs and extravagance, and that Mens Lives ſhould be anſwerable to their Creed? And accordingly the ſame Author repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents them by a logick natural enough, arguing at this rate in the very words that follow: <hi>Come on therefore, let us enjoy the good things that are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, let us ſpeedily uſe the creatures as in youth: let us fill our ſelves with coſtly wine and ointments, and let no flower of the graſs ſpring by us: let none of us go with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his part of voluptuouſneſs, let us leave tokens of our joyfulneſs in every place; for this is our portion and our lot. Let us oppreſs the poor righteous man, let us not ſpare the widow, nor reverence the ancient gray hairs of the aged, let our ſtrength be the law of Juſtice; let us lye in wait for the righteous, and examin him with deceitfulneſs and torture, that we may know his meekneſs, and prove his patience, and let us condemn him with a ſhameful death. Theſe things</hi> (ſays he) <hi>they did ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, and as for the mysteries of God they knew them not, neither hoped they for the ways of righteouſneſs, nor diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a reward for blameleſs ſouls.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:95249:6"/>
            <p>Such are the Inferences, that naturally flow from the Articles of the Epicures and the Atheiſts Creed. The folly and abſurdneſs whereof I ſhall not endeavour to expoſe, themſelves would not be content that they ſhould be purſued to their proper iſſues. For were Conſcience once diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged from the obligations of Religion, they could not reaſonably hope to be one minute ſecure and undiſturbed in their beloved Pleaſures and Poſſeſſions, but that the longeſt Sword and the ſtrongeſt Arm would ſoon put in a claim for the biggeſt ſhare. Indeed I am loth to think ſo ill of human Nature, as to believe, however the temptation may ſucceed with a few, that any conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable part of Mankind ſhould fall under ſo black a charge. There is a natural ſenſe of God impreſſed upon the Minds of Men, Principles born and bred up with us, and which freely bear witneſs to God and Goodneſs, which may for a time be ſuppreſſed and laid a ſleep, but can hardly by any arts be ſo choaked and ſtifled, but that upon every occaſion this vital Principle will awake, ſtart up and betray it ſelf. When there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſubtil Agent finds this Engin too weak to prevail, at leaſt on the generality of Mankind, he has another at hand, to keep them off from en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging in a ſober and a virtuous courſe, and that is</p>
            <p n="2">II. Secondly, by making falſe and undue
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:95249:6"/>repreſentations of Religion, by dreſſing it up in ſo unlovely a garb, as ſhall fright Men from the embraces of it: When he cannot prevail with Men to doubt of the truth, he will perſwade them to queſtion the goodneſs and equity of Religion. And a twofold artifice is commonly made uſe of, to prejudice Religion in the Minds of Men, that its reſtraints are unjuſt and unreaſonable, and that the commands of it are difficult or impoſſible.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Religion is look'd upon as a tyrannical Incroachment upon the natural Rights and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges of Mankind, as laying unjuſt and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable reſtraints upon Men, ſuch as enſlave our free born faculties, confine our native ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites, and tye us up from all agreeable pleaſures and delights; that we cannot be good, but we muſt ceaſe to be Men, nor embrace Religion, but we muſt put off humanity; that certainly God never intended His Laws ſhould be an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion and a torment to Mankind, nor ever gave them ſuch vaſt appetites and deſires, or furniſhed the Creation with ſuch variety of beautiful and grateful Objects, meerly to tantalize their deſires; that it's in vain to talk of freedom and liberty, when we are bound up by the Laws of Juſtice and Righteouſneſs, that we muſt not exert our power, though never ſo convenient an advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage be offered to greaten and enrich our ſelves;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:95249:7"/>when we cannot ſecurely gratifie our inclinations with thoſe pleaſures, that are acceptable to our ſenſes and our appetites, but Religion muſt inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, with the precepts of Sobriety and Chaſtity, Temperance and Moderation, to control and interrupt us.</p>
            <p>But if this Temptation ſignifie any thing, it pleads for an univerſal exemption from all Laws, there being no Law without a reſtraint, and then what becomes of Obedience to natural Parents or civil Powers? what of our Obligations to God as our great Parent and Benefactor? The Laws of our Creature-ſhip and dependance do neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily and indiſpenſibly ſubject us to God as our Creator, and we can as ſoon ceaſe to be Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as become independent: And if any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraints be neceſſary and allowable, what can be more fit and comely, than thoſe which Religion lays upon us? ſo proper and agreeable to our Natures, ſo conducive to our Intereſt, ſo neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to the Peace and Happineſs of the World, that were they generally thrown off, particular Perſons and publick Societies would be imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately hurried into diſorder and a <hi>Chaos,</hi> and Mankind become like a Forreſt of wild Beaſts, equally ſavage, and mutually deſtructive of one another. Nor are we debarred any delights and ſatisfactions, but what are vicious and irregular,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:95249:7"/>diſhonourable and deſtructive to our Natures, and a diſparagement both to our Religion and our Reaſon, and the abſtaining from which does immediately conduce to make us happy. But it's repreſented</p>
            <p>Secondly, to the diſadvantage of Religion, that the Precepts of it are difficult, if not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible; that it <hi>binds upon us heavy burthens and grievous to be born,</hi> and what it commands is <hi>an hard ſaying, and who can bear it?</hi> eſpecially in our fallen and degenerate ſtate, which has laid us under ſo much weakneſs and impotency, that conſidering the neceſſary and unavoidable infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of our Nature, 'tis no great wonder if we do ſlip and fall; when we cannot rectifie what is crooked, nor have ſtrength enough to bear up againſt the ſtream that comes full upon us. <hi>Can the Leopard change his ſpots? or the</hi> Ethiopian <hi>waſh white his skin?</hi> If God deſigned we ſhould lead an innocent and ſpotleſs life, why did He not reform and mend the Faculties of the Soul, or render it incapable to prevaricate and ſin againſt Him? <hi>Nay but, O man! who art thou that replieſt againſt God? Shall the thing formed ſay to him that formed it, why haſt thou made me thus? God made man upright, and himſelf ſought out many inventions.</hi> Nor even in the preſent ſtate wherein we are, does God require any thing of us that is impoſſible.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:95249:8"/>
               <hi>His Law is holy, juſt, and good;</hi> His <hi>yoke is eaſie, and his burthen light; His commandements are not grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous,</hi> but that <hi>whoever is born of God overcomes the world.</hi> He is not wanting to render our Duty eaſie to us; He encourages our hopes with the promiſes of an infinite reward, and by the threatenings of a future and intolerable vengeance, awakens our fears to a due care and caution. He aſſiſts our infirmities with a ſtrength proportionable to our weakneſs, and the neceſſities of our ſtate; ſo that though the temptations that aſſault us be ſtrong and mighty, yet <hi>greater is he that is in us, than he that is in the world:</hi> The Grace and Spirit of God are an unconquerable Principle, for which no command can be too hard or heavy, and theſe God is always ready to afford, and never with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draws from any, 'till by a long train and courſe of impiety, and many wilful and obſtinate refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals, they have forfeited the aids of Divine Grace, and rendered themſelves unworthy of it. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that, there are few difficulties in Religion, but what our own folly have made to be ſo, and thoſe that are, as 'tis in all Arts and Inſtitutions, are worſt at firſt, which being once broken and conquered, the main difficulties of a Religious Life are overcome, and every ſtep of the way after becomes more pleaſant and delightful.</p>
            <p n="3">III. Another artifice, by which <hi>Satan</hi> is wont
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:95249:8"/>to obſtruct real piety and a good life, is by tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pting Men to place all Religion in a few empty and external pretenſions to piety and holineſs, devoid of the inward life and ſpirit of Religion. Some kind of Religion moſt Men are for, in ſpite of all the projects and deſigns of Hell, which becauſe <hi>Satan</hi> cannot hinder, he'll take care it ſhall be ſuch, as ſhall do them little good; and Men are forward enough to comply with that, which bids faireſt to carry them to Heaven upon the cheapeſt terms. And hence it is, that inſtead of a ſincere and ſubſtantial piety, an inward ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection of the Soul to God, and a conformity of the Life to the eternal Laws of Truth and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, they generally take up in a looſe profeſſion, in a few ſlighty obſervances, and ſuperficial for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malities of Devotion. This is too ſadly viſible among the ſeveral pretending parties to Religion in the World. Some there are, whoſe beſt title to Religion, is the accommodating themſelves to ſome particular mode of adminiſtration, that they have joyned themſelves to this Mans Church, or that Mans Congregation, and are warm and active to eſpouſe and promote the Intereſts of a little Tribe or Faction. Others ſpend their zeal for the Orthodoxy of their private and particular Notions and Opinions, regardleſs at the ſame time of Love and Charity, the good of the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:95249:9"/>Church, and the peace of the World, without which all our clamour is but a blind and intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate zeal, a bitter and unwarrantable paſſion, conſecrated by a more venerable Name. There are, that pleaſe themſelves with the number and frequency of their Devotions, pray much, and hear often, and ſo far 'tis well; but then never regard with what honeſty of mind, and ſprightly vivacity of affection, their Incenſe is offered up, nay poſſibly reckon into the bargain, that the cuſtomary diſcharge of theſe ſhall redeem their credit with Heaven, for all the miſcarriages of their lives. The <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſes,</hi> above all the Sects in the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church, entit'led them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the higheſt ſtrictneſſes and ſeverities of Religion, faſted at every turn, gave alms twice a week, prayed in every corner of the ſtreets, and ſome of them did almoſt nothing elſe but pray; and yet theſe grave and demure pretenders, made uſe of theſe only as a cloak to cover their malice and ill nature, their rapine and violence, and the greateſt villany and oppreſſion; they prayed to God, and at the ſame time <hi>robbed the Orphan and devoured Widows houſes, tythed mint, anniſe, and cummin,</hi> and <hi>neglected judgment, mercy, and fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity, the greater and weightier matters of the Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How great a part of the Chriſtian World is trained up in meer outward forms and ritual
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:95249:9"/>ſervices, in eaſie devotions and cheap perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances, is too notorious to inſiſt upon. When the main of a Chriſtians Duty ſhall be reckoned to conſiſt in a few <hi>bodily exerciſes,</hi> and corporal ſeverities, in numbering over a ſet of prayers, which the Votary it may be does neither mind, nor is capable to underſtand. When one act of contrition, an eaſie or a trifling pennance, a ſhort confeſſion, and an abſolution, ſhall be thought enough, even in the <hi>article of death,</hi> to put a Man into a ſtate of ſalvation, and to ſecure his happineſs in another world. Repentance, alas! is the great buſineſs of a Man's Life, and is then ſincere and effectual to the purpoſes of Religion, when 'tis attended with a real and a hearty reformation; and without this, ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Indulgences cannot profit him, nor all the Abſolutions in the world relieve the Conſcience of a guilty Sinner.
<note place="margin">Mich. 6.7, 8.</note> 
               <hi>Will the Lord be pleaſed with thouſands of Rams? or ten thouſands of Rivers of Oyl? He hath ſhewed thee, O man! what is good, and what the Lord doth require of thee, to do juſtly, and to love mercy, and to walk humbly with God.</hi> The ſumm is this: Religion is an inward and a vital Principle, a conſtant ſpring of uniform and entire Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, that lyes not in forms and ſhews, in ſubtilties and diſputes, in <hi>Schemes</hi> of ſpeech, or <hi>Syſtems</hi> of opinions, in glorious pretences, or
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:95249:10"/>being of a Sect or Party, but in a divine life, in a great love to God, and a veneration of his Perfections, a dread of his Power, and a reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence for his Laws, in the mortification of our paſſions, and the ſubjection of our irregular de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, in being meek and humble, compaſſionate and charitable, juſt and righteous: It is not an art of ſpeaking finely,
<note place="margin">Mat. 7.21.</note> but of living well, <hi>Not every one that ſayeth, Lord, Lord, ſhall enter into the Kingdom of Heaven, but he that doth the Will of my Father that is in Heaven:</hi> 'Tis the participation of a Divine Nature, and a conformity to the Image of God, the <hi>keeping a conſcience void of offence, both towards God and men.</hi> And whoever takes up ſhort of this, ſits down in the porch, and contents himſelf with a <hi>name to live,</hi> and may have Religion enough to make him an Hypocrite, but not truly to entitle him to be a Chriſtian. <hi>The Kingdom of God is not meats and drinks,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 14.17.</note> it is not to be exact and curious, as the <hi>Jews</hi> were, about abundance of little obſervances, and ritual de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions, <hi>but righteouſneſs, and peace, and joy in the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">IV. <hi>Fourthly, Satan</hi> too often prevails upon Men, by tempting them to ſuch Vices, as have a ſhadow and reſemblance of Virtue. The politick and crafty Spirit knows very well, that Sin is of ſo black a nature, that it will never take, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:95249:10"/>with the more ſober and conſidering ſort of Men, in its own naked ſhape, and therefore dreſſes it up in a better garb, and calls it by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther name. Few Men but would recoil and ſtart at a down-right temptation to murder, but when 'tis whetted by revenge, and ſet off as the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining our reputation and our honour, it goes down readily without control. <hi>Caiphas</hi> 'tis like had no perſonal pique and quarrel at our bleſſed Saviour, when he adviſed the <hi>Sanhedrim</hi> to cut him off; but he did it under the ſpecious notion of a common good, and the publick ſecurity of the Nation. How came <hi>Satan</hi> to actuate St. <hi>Paul</hi> with a ſpirit of ſo much bitterneſs and animoſity, ſuch a furious and paſſionate ſpleen, againſt the primitive Believers, but only that he perſwaded him, that the Glory of God, and the Honour of his Religion, did ſo deeply lye at ſtake? What makes Avarice ſpread ſo far, and that with many, otherwiſe high pretenders to Religion, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it aſſumes to it ſelf the plauſible pretext of a laudable diligence and frugality, and a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable care to make proviſion for our ſelves and families, warranted and enjoyned by the Laws of Nature and Religion? And under the ſhadow of this, the Tempter leads Men into all the extravagant irregularities, into which a greedy and rapacious Mind is capable to betray
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:95249:11"/>them. Pride never ſpreads its plumes with more ſucceſs, than when 'tis recommended as a piece of neatneſs and gentility, and a juſt valuing of our ſelves according to our deſert and quality. Many a Man would never be betrayed into the exceſſes of riot and intemperance, did he not look upon it as an argument of a free generous mind, and a piece of innocent good fellowſhip and ſociety. And thus <hi>Satan</hi> very ſucceſsfully leads Men into <hi>works of darkneſs,</hi> by appearing to them as an <hi>Angel of light,</hi> and puts off his tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations under the notion, either of what is vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, or at leaſt what is uſeful and lawful to them.</p>
            <p n="5">V. I ſhall mention but one art and <hi>ſtratagem</hi> more, whereby this great Enemy recommends his temptations with advantage to us, and that is, by improving the influence of powerful and prevalent Examples. Mankind is of a ſociable and pliant temper, eaſily drawn aſide with the moſt, eſpecially with <hi>a multitude to do evil,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the by as of corrupt Nature runs that way. We are apt to look upon it as ſome kind of ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and patronage, to ſin in company, where every one bears his ſhare of the guilt and ſhame, and ſo it ſeems leſs by being divided, like a great Stream that is cut into little Rivulets. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample is a mighty argument, and one of <hi>Satan</hi>'s
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:95249:11"/>moſt effectual ſnares, and which many times, without great care and reſolution, there is no way to avoid; for the corruption of manners, has I know not how introduced a kind of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, of doing as the company does wherein we are, and to refuſe it, is look'd upon as a treſpaſs againſt the Laws of Civility and good Manners, and the Man accounted either a Clown or an Hypocrite, that will not venture as far as the reſt, and <hi>run with them into the ſame exceſs of riot.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the force of the temptation is ſo much the ſtronger, by how much thoſe whom we follow, are perſons for whom we have a more peculiar eſteem and veneration, or by whom we have been obliged, as our Benefactors. We have a natural regard and reverence for our betters, and are prone to imitate them by an implicit Faith. The vulgar part of Mankind look upon their Superiours, that as they ſtand under higher and ſtronger obligations to Virtue and Piety, ſo they are furniſhed with happier advantages of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the true natures and differences of things, than other Men, and accordingly from them are apt to take the common meaſures of good or evil, and to defend themſelves with the warrant and authority of thoſe that are above them. The Examples of Great Men give Laws to conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:95249:12"/>and are able to add a reputation either to Vice or Virtue, and one ſuch inſtance ſhall ſooner prevail with Men to ſet upon thoſe things that are <hi>juſt and pure, lovely and of good report,</hi> than an hundred arguments ſhall perſwade them: As, on the other hand, Vice is never more fatally proſperous and ſucceſsful, than when it has the patronage of great Examples to recommend it.</p>
            <p>By theſe few Inſtances, we ſee the lot and portion of the preſent ſtate, what ſnares and <hi>ſtratagems,</hi> what policies and devices, we are expoſed to on every ſide, what troops of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations are round about us; that therefore it concerns us to ſtand continually upon our guard, to keep our conſiderations awake, to preſerve our conſciences quick and tender, to be infinitely watchful, that our foot be not taken in any of thoſe ſnares, that are purpoſely laid to ruin us, not only in this, but (which is unconceivably of more importance) in the other life. For a courſe of impiety, has not only a fatal and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant influence upon the affairs of the preſent ſtate, it does not only tend to conſume the eſtate, or blaſt the reputation, or waſte the body, diſtract and torment the mind, and render every condition troubleſome and uneaſie, theſe, alas! are <hi>but the beginning of ſorrows,</hi> in reſpect of that portion of miſery, that awaits the Sinner in the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:95249:12"/>future ſtate, when the wrath and diſpleaſure of the Almighty ſhall finally overtake him, and <hi>come upon him to the uttermoſt.</hi> For the other World is the proper ſcene and ſtage, whereon the Divine Juſtice ſhall ride in triumph in the executions of its vengeance; when Conſcience ſhall be let looſe with all its ſtings, and perpetually prey upon it ſelf; when the remembrances of an ill-ſpent life, and the ſad reflections upon its paſt ſins and pleaſures, ſhall be always preſſing in upon it, and the Soul unable either to deny or ſhift off the evidence; when nothing ſhall be able to mitigate the grief, or to beguile the ſenſe of it; when there ſhall be no raviſhing objects, external pleaſures, no muſical Airs, or boon Companions, to charm Conſcience aſleep again, no intermitting fits of eaſe, but the Soul groaning under perpetual paroxyſms of rage and terrour.</p>
            <p>The conſideration whereof, ought to allarm our fears, that if there be any care of our ſelves, any ſerious regards of our eternal ſtate, we may be wiſe in time, before it be too late, <hi>recover our ſelves out of the ſnare of the Devil,</hi> and become <hi>ſober and vigilant; becauſe our adverſary goes about, ſeeking whom he may devour.</hi> 'Tis no contemptible Enemy that we have to deal with, nor the leſs to be feared becauſe inviſible, nay 'tis this renders him more capable of ſucceeding in his attempts
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:95249:13"/>upon us; for by this means he maintains a nearer and more ſecret intercourſe with the Spirits of Men, makes more undiſcerned and inſenſible approaches, and ſtorms the walls before we are aware: He is admirably acute and ſubtil, to plant his engins, to make his batteries in the weakeſt part, he narrowly obſerves our tempers and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, our fears and ſcruples, our diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and inclinations, and accordingly adapts his temptations to us with moſt ſucceſs,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Salluſt.</hi> de Bell. Catal. c. 14. p. 32.</note> 
               <hi>Ut cujuſque ſtudium ex aetate flagrabat,</hi> as the Hiſtorian re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marques concerning the Arts of <hi>Catalin,</hi> in every period of life he furniſhes Men with what is moſt agreeable to their age and temper.</p>
            <p>But, alas! though Men had no foreign Enemy from without to make war upon them, though there were no ſubtil Tempter to ſeduce them, there is an Enemy within their own breaſts, that lays trains to ruin them; their own corrupt and vicious inclinations ſet open the door, and hurry them forth to meet the temptation that's coming towards them:
<note place="margin">Jam. 1.14.</note> 
               <hi>Every man is tempted, when he is drawn aſide of his own luſt, and enticed.</hi> Herein lyes <hi>Satans</hi> great advantage, he knows our ſtrength is ſmall, our propenſions to ſin impetuous and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and how apt we are to be betrayed by our appetites and paſſions. All external Objects, though never ſo raviſhing and delightful, could
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:95249:13"/>make no impreſſion, were there not a party within, that's falſe to the true intereſts of the Soul. <hi>Satan,</hi> as potent and crafty as he is, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not raviſh our wills, nor force our inclinations; the worſt he can do, is to prompt and perſwade, to watch advantages, and adminiſter ſuitable ſollicitations, but cannot compel us to entertain them. No Man is undone, but himſelf is the cauſe on't, he that would not, cannot be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, provided he keep his reſolutions fix'd and ſtedfaſt. This is the true way of conqueſt and victory over <hi>Satan, reſiſt the Devil,
<note place="margin">Jam. 4.7.</note> and he will flye from you;</hi> if we do but make good our ground, his temptations will vaniſh and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appear.</p>
            <p>Let us then treaſure up in our Minds a great ſenſe of God and of our ſelves, let us ſuffer Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience freely to diſcharge its duty, and <hi>have our ſenſes exerciſed to diſcern betwixt good and evil.</hi> Let us reverence the greatneſs and nobility of our Natures, which are of a more Divine frame and temper, than to be proſtituted and defiled. There's no real Evil in this World but Sin, other things may be evil to us, but that's evil in it ſelf: There's an eternal and unalterable deformity in its nature, which no plauſible pretences can wipe off: As Virtue and Goodneſs are in themſelves lovely and excellent, ſo Wickedneſs is eſſentially vile and baſe.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:95249:14"/>
            <p>Let all opportunities and occaſions of Vice be avoided, with a quick and a jealous care; a temptation is eaſilier prevented, than removed, when once it has thruſt it ſelf upon the Sinner. 'Tis good to ſuſpect lawful things: Men cannot ſafely uſe their utmoſt liberty; he that will go juſt as far as he may, 'tis no wonder if he be tempted to go further than he ought. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is lawful, may not be expedient, eſpecially when 'tis likely to be abuſed unto exceſs. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity is treacherous and unfaithful; where no immediate danger is apprehended, care is uſually laid aſide, and liberty degenerates into licentiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. <hi>Bleſſed is he that feareth always,</hi> that chuſes rather to ſit down ſhort, and to deny himſelf in ſome warrantable ſatisfactions, than preſume to venture to the end of his line. 'Tis hard to diſtinguiſh the utmoſt bounds, and the nice limits between good and evil, and therefore ſafeſt to keep within what's evidently fit and lawful. <hi>When thou ſitteſt to eat with a Ruler</hi> (ſays the Wiſe Man) <hi>put a knife to thy throat,
<note place="margin">Prov. 23.1, 2.</note> if thou be a man given to appetite;</hi> that is, be exceeding wary, and govern thine appetite by the ſevereſt meaſures of ſobriety, becauſe exceſs, at ſuch a time, is much readier to ſteal upon us, than when a temptation to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperance is with open face preſented to us.</p>
            <p>We ſhould frequently review our lives, and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:95249:14"/>call our actions to a ſevere and impartial exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, that we may know what is their ſpring and fountain, what their tendency and inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and what will be the conſequence and the iſſue of them; and that if <hi>Satan</hi> have conveyed in a ſuggeſtion in diſguiſe, we may pull off the vizor, and reſent it in its own form and ſhape. And this account ſhould be taken, as near as may be, upon the doing of every action, or as ſoon as ever the thoughts are freed from the preſent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbrances that are upon them.
<note place="margin">Vid. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. n. 40. &amp;c.</note> The <hi>Pythagoreans</hi> were taught, thrice every night to call themſelves to an account for the actions of the preceding day;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Senec.</hi> de Ira l. 3. c. 36. p. 87.</note> and <hi>Sextius,</hi> the Philoſopher, never uſed to go to bed, 'till he had firſt reaſoned and expoſtulated with himſelf, <hi>What evil habit have I cured to day? what vice have I reſiſted? wherein am I better than I was before?</hi> And certainly, would Chriſtians accuſtom themſelves more to this excellent courſe, they would quickly find a double advantage flow from it; that repentance, and the reforming of our lives, would be infinitely more eaſie and tolerable, and that our minds would be trained up to a greater warineſs and circumſpection, and to keep a more ſtrict and ſevere hand over our own lives and actions: Nothing being more inſtrumental to reſtrain impiety, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote virtue and a good life, than to bring the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:95249:15"/>actions of every day <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<note place="margin">Com. in Aur. Carm. p. 209.</note> (as <hi>Hierocles</hi> expreſſes it) before the <hi>Tribunal</hi> of Conſcience, and to paſs a juſt and an unbyaſſed ſentence upon our ſelves.</p>
            <p>This method once eſtabliſhed, would weaken the power of vicious habits, and withdraw the fewel that enflames the fire, 'twould ruin the party which the Enemy has within us. Men are commonly betrayed by thoſe of their own houſe, the Enemy maintains correſpondence with their inordinate appetites and inclinations, and by them ſurpriſes and pulls them down. Every irregular paſſion ſubdued and mortified, is a breach made up in the soul, and leaves leſs hold for <hi>Satan</hi> to faſten his Engins and Deſigns upon it. But above all we muſt ſollicit Heaven, that God would enable us to defeat and diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point the plots and ſubtilties of the Tempter: <hi>Watch and pray, that ye enter not into temptation:</hi> Our Lord has made it part of our daily addreſs to Heaven, that God <hi>would not lead,</hi> that is, not ſuffer us to be lead <hi>into temptation, but deliver us</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, from the power and prevalency of the Devil. He is too hard for us in our own ſtrength, but God has ſaid, <hi>His Grace ſhall be ſufficient for us.</hi> If we be ſincere and hearty in our ſtriving, we have an inviſible aid at hand, the aſſiſtance of God's Grace and Spirit, a ſupply
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:95249:15"/>infinitely beyond all the powers of <hi>Satan.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, God is pleaſed to animate our Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, and encourage our induſtry and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeverance, with the promiſe of a mighty re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: <hi>To him that overcomes,
<note place="margin">Rev. 3.21.</note> I will grant to ſit with me in my Throne, even as I alſo overcame, and am ſet down with my Father in his Throne.</hi> The Wiſe and Good God does not oblige us to eternal labours, to grapple with endleſs difficulties and oppoſitions, there is a term and period fix'd to our preſent warfare, a time coming, when theſe tryals ſhall ceaſe, and our preſent troubles be ſwallowed up in infinite joys and pleaſures. What then remains? but that we <hi>be ſtrong in the Lord, and in the power of his might;</hi> that <hi>we take unto our ſelves the whole armour of God,</hi> and be thereby enabled <hi>to ſtand againſt the wiles of the Devil; praying always with all prayer and ſupplication in the ſpirit, and watching thereunto with all perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance;</hi> that after all the conflicts and difficulties of the preſent life, we may <hi>be able to withſtand in the evil day, and having done all to ſtand.</hi> Now <hi>the God of all Grace, who hath called us unto his eternal glory by</hi> Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>make you perfect, ſtabliſh, ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, ſettle you. To Him be Glory and Dominion for ever and ever.</hi> AMEN.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
